Finding Aid for Paul Hillegonds Papers 1964-1996
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Paul C. Hillegonds Papers 1964-1996, 1978-1996
Hillegonds, Paul C., 1949-
12 linear feet
Republican member of the Michigan House of Representatives, 1979-1996; press/publicity files, correspondence, speeches, political campaign files, legislative files.
9737 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Paul C. Hillegonds and came to the library in 1996. Donor no. 8539
The collection is open for research.
Born and raised in Holland, Michigan, Paul C. Hillegonds graduated from the University of Michigan in 1971 with a degree in political science. He subsequently earned a law degree from the Thomas M. Cooley Law School in 1986. Commencing immediately in 1971 upon a career in politics and public service, Hillegonds worked as administrative aide to Congressman Philip Ruppe who represented Michigan's Upper Peninsula. In addition, Hillegonds managed Ruppe's reelection campaigns in 1974 and 1976 as well as his unsuccessful bids to obtain the Republican nomination to the U.S. Senate in 1978 and 1982.
In 1978, Hillegonds was himself elected to the Michigan House of Representatives for the 54th District, which then included Allegan and part of Barry counties and which was subsequently redrawn as the 88th District to include Allegan County only. Hillegonds would serve in the legislature for the next 18 years until 1996 at which time he left office and assumed the position of president of New Detroit, Inc.
While in the legislature, Hillegonds assumed a series of increasingly responsible positions. When he first came to the House in 1978, Hillegonds was appointed to chair the House Republican Campaign Committee, a position he held from 1979 to 1982. In 1983, he was elected by his Republican colleagues to be Assistant Minority Floor Leader and in 1987 he was elected House Minority Floor Leader (or Republican Leader). In 1993, with the House split evenly between the two parties, Hillegonds was elected co-speaker along with his Democratic colleague Curtis Hertel; and in 1995, with a Republican majority, he was elected to the post of speaker.
As a lawmaker, Hillegonds was especially involved in legislation to reform the state's workers' compensation and unemployment insurance laws. In addition, Hillegonds helped to draft property tax relief legislation and was a persistent advocate of "sunset" legislation and school finance reform.
The collection covers the period of ca. 1964 to 1996, but the bulk of the papers fall within the period when he served in the state legislature, 1978 to 1996. The materials have been arranged into eight series:
Biographical/personal -- Box 1
Press/publicity -- Boxes 1-3, 12
Correspondence - Box 4
Speeches -- Box 5
Political Campaign Files -- Boxes 6-7
Legislative Files -- Boxes 7-11
Office Staff -- Box 11
Miscellaneous -- Box 11
The Paul C. Hillegonds collection concerns the political and legislative career of Paul Hillegonds, a long-term member of the Michigan House of Representatives from western Michigan. The collection documents Hillegonds' campaigns for office and his activities within the state Republican Party as well as his duties within the legislature and his interest in certain key pieces of legislation.
Subjects:
Hillegonds, Paul C., 1949-; Allegan County (Mich.); Allegan State Game Area (Mich.); Education--Finance--Law and legislation--Michigan.; Environmental law--Michigan.; Hertel, Curtis.; Michigan. Legislature. House of Representatives.; Michigan--Politics and government--1971-1980.; Michigan--Politics and government--1981-1990.; Michigan--Politics and government--1991-2000.; Natural resources--Law and legislation--Michigan.; Republican Party (Mich.); Ruppe, Philip E., 1926-; Workers' compensation--Law and legislation--Michigan.; Saugatuck Dunes State Park (Mich.); Sunset reviews of government programs--Law and legislation--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Hillegonds, Paul C., 1949-; Legislators--Michigan.; Michigan. Legislature. House of Representatives.; Political elections--Michigan.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Biographical/personal
  - Biographical information (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Awards received (Box 1)
  - Article written for Reformed Review, entitled, "One Christian's View from the Statehouse" (Box 1)
  - Articles written (miscellaneous) (Box 1)
  - Articles written for newspapers (Box 1)
  - Letters to the editor (Box 1)
- Press/publicity files
  - Press releases
    - 1978-1989, 7 folders (Box 1)
      (also include photocopies of clippings about PH)
    - 1990-1995, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clippings 1978-1995
    - 1978-1995 (Box 2)
      (largely unprocessed)
    - 1978-1995 (Box 12)
  - Lansing Diary (PH newsletter/press release), 1979-1996, 18 folders (Box 3)
  - Newsletters (various), 1980-1991: Official News, Legislative Review, and Lansing Diary, 1 folders (Box 3)
- Correspondence
  - 1995-1996 (Box 4)
    arranged chronologically
- Speeches
  - circa 1980-1996 (Box 5)
    (mainly arranged alphabetically by title of speech or function at which the speech was given)
- Political Campaign Files
  - 1974-1991 (Box 6)
    (includes PH's work on behalf of Philip Ruppe and as chair of the House Republican Campaign Committee)
  - 1992-1996 (Box 7)
- Legislative Files
  Of most interest to researchers interested in public policy discussions are the Legislative Files. These have been divided into different subseries, the most important of which concern legislation and or public policy issues with which Hillegonds was most actively involved. These included education finance reform, workers' compensation reform, so-called "Sunset" legislation, and a variety of environmental causes, particularly relating to Hillegonds district. Noteworthy here are his files on the Allegan State Game Area and the Saugatuck Dunes State Park.
  A significant portion of the Legislative Files pertains to the period of 1993 to 1996 when Hillegonds was first co-speaker of the House and then speaker of the Michigan House of Representatives. These materials include documentation of the agreements between the two political parties on how the House should operate while neither party had a majority. Bulkier files in this subseries relate to Hillegonds' work with the Legislative Council and as a member of the National Conference of State Legislatures.
  - Voting record, attendance record, and legislation sponsored (Box 7)
  - Relations with other branches of state government
    - Governor's Office (John Engler), 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Michigan Supreme Court (Box 7)
  - Relations with federal government (Box 7)
  - Legislation/public policy issues-General
    - Abortion (alternative to) (Box 7)
    - Abortion (services abortion clinics need to provide) (Box 7)
    - Accountability Task Force (Box 7)
    - Allegan Bridge (Box 7)
    - Block Parent Program (Box 7)
    - Budget-Target setting meetings (Box 7)
    - Campaign finance 1979 (Box 7)
    - Corrections (Dept. of)-Howard Leroux file (Box 7)
    - Economic development 1994 (Box 7)
    - Education (Clark Durant) (Box 7)
    - Ethics (Box 7)
    - Identification cards (state) (Box 7)
    - Legislative accomplishments 1995 (Box 7)
    - Licensing of barbers and cosmetologists (Box 8)
    - Licensing of hearing aid dealers (Box 8)
    - Lobby registration act (Box 8)
    - Native American Gaming Pact (Box 8)
    - Prompt payment legislation, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Property tax appeal package (Box 8)
    - Railroad (city of Hopkins v. Penn Central, offer of railroad to sell) (Box 8)
    - Railroad car derailments (Box 8)
    - Recount procedures revision (Box 8)
    - RSVP (PH responds to constituent mailings with views on legislation) (Box 8)
    - School finance reform, 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Sunset legislation, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Sunset legislation, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Superfund (Box 9)
    - Taxation-Personal exemption tax indexing (Box 9)
    - Worker's Compensation (Box 9)
  - Legislation/public policy issues-environment
    - Allegan Dam Purchase Project (Box 9)
    - Allegan State Game Area, 3 folders (Box 9)
    - Kal-Haven Trail (Box 9)
    - Noordhouse Dunes (Box 9)
    - Saugatuck Dunes State Park, 1 volumes; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Saugatuck Dunes State Park, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - House of Representatives leadership and related
    - Allotments 1994 (Box 10)
    - Audit 1993 (Box 10)
    - Co-speakership with Curtis Hertel
      - Memoranda 1993-1994 (Box 10)
      - Signed agreements and related legislation (Box 10)
      - Letters of congratulations (Box 10)
    - Dodak, Lewis (speaker) (Box 10)
    - House Fiscal Agency, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - House organization and rules, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - House Republican Task Force on Illegal Drugs notebook (Box 10)
    - Leadership
      - General (Box 10)
      - Leader's report (Box 10)
      - Work group reports (Box 10)
    - Legislative Council 1991-1996, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Legislative Retirement 1988-1996 (Box 11)
    - National Conference of State Legislatures 1995-1996 (Box 11)
    - Republican caucus meetings 1995-1996 (Box 11)
    - State Officers Compensation Commission (Box 11)
- Office Staff
  - Office memos and press releases April 1995-December 1996, 3 folders (Box 11)
  - Staff flow memos (Box 11)
  - Staff status memos (Box 11)
- Miscellaneous
  - Detroit Free Press (Box 11)
  - Endorsements (Box 11)
  - Oaths of Office (Box 11)
  - Ruppe, Phil (memos of PH to) (Box 11)
  - Waldron, Robert (oral interview) (Box 11)
  - Unfiled miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 11)